<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publicaciones on Rafael Álvarez García</title>
    <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publicaciones on Rafael Álvarez García</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Non-minimal Elliptic Threefolds at Infinite Distance II: Asymptotic Physics</title>
      <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/non-minimal-threefolds-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/non-minimal-threefolds-ii/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;with Seung-Joo Lee and Timo Weigand&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We interpret infinite-distance limits in the complex structure moduli space of F-theory compactifications to six dimensions in the light of general ideas in quantum gravity. The limits we focus on arise from non-minimal singularities in the elliptic fiber over curves in a Hirzebruch surface base, which do not admit a crepant resolution. Such degenerations take place along infinite directions in the non-perturbative brane moduli space in F-theory. A blow-up procedure, detailed generally in Part I of this project, gives rise to an internal space consisting of a union of log Calabi-Yau threefolds glued together along their boundaries. We geometrically classify the resulting configurations for genus-zero single infinite-distance limits. Special emphasis is put on the structure of singular fibers in codimension zero and one. As our main result, we interpret the central fiber of these degenerations as endpoints of a decompactification limit with six-dimensional defects. The conclusions rely on an adiabatic limit to gain information on the asymptotically massless states from the structure of vanishing cycles. We also compare our analysis to the heterotic dual description where available. Our findings are in agreement with general expectations from quantum gravity and provide further evidence for the Emergent String Conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-minimal Elliptic Threefolds at Infinite Distance I: Log Calabi-Yau Resolutions</title>
      <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/non-minimal-threefolds-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/non-minimal-threefolds-i/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;with Seung-Joo Lee and Timo Weigand&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study infinite-distance limits in the complex structure moduli space of elliptic Calabi-Yau threefolds. In F-theory compactifications to six dimensions, such limits include infinite-distance trajectories in the non-perturbative open string moduli space. The limits are described as degenerations of elliptic threefolds whose central elements exhibit non-minimal elliptic fibers, in the Kodaira sense, over curves on the base. We show how these non-crepant singularities can be removed by a systematic sequence of blow-ups of the base, leading to a union of log Calabi-Yau spaces glued together along their boundaries. We identify criteria for the blow-ups to give rise to open chains or more complicated trees of components and analyse the blow-up geometry. While our results are general and applicable to all non-minimal degenerations of Calabi-Yau threefolds in codimension one, we exemplify them in particular for elliptic threefolds over Hirzebruch surface base spaces. We also explain how to extract the gauge algebra for F-theory probing such reducible asymptotic geometries. This analysis is the basis for a detailed F-theory interpretation of the associated infinite-distance limits that will be provided in a companion paper.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Membrane Limits in Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/membrane-limits-quantum-gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/membrane-limits-quantum-gravity/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;with Daniel Kläwer and Timo Weigand&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is expected that infinite distance limits in the moduli space of quantum gravity are accompanied by a tower of light states. In view of the emergent string conjecture, this tower must either induce a decompactification or correspond to the emergence of a tensionless critical string. We study the consistency conditions implied by this conjecture on the asymptotic behavior of quantum gravity under dimensional reduction. If the emergent string descends from a (2+1)-dimensional membrane in a higher-dimensional theory, we find that such a membrane must parametrically decouple from the Kaluza-Klein scale. We verify this censorship against emergent membrane limits, where the membrane would sit at the Kaluza-Klein scale, in the hypermultiplet moduli space of Calabi-Yau 3-fold compactifications of string/M-theory. At the classical level, a putative membrane limit arises, up to duality, from an M5-brane wrapping the asymptotically shrinking special Lagrangian 3-cycle corresponding to the Strominger-Yau-Zaslow fiber of the Calabi-Yau. We show how quantum corrections in the moduli space obstruct such a limit and instead lead to a decompactification to 11 dimensions, where the role of the M5- and M2-branes are interchanged.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analytic Periods via Twisted Symmetric Squares</title>
      <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/analytic-periods-twisted-symmetric-squares/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/analytic-periods-twisted-symmetric-squares/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;with Lorenz Schlechter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study the symmetric square of Picard-Fuchs operators of genus one curves and the thereby induced generalized Clausen identities. This allows the computation of analytic expressions for the periods of all one-parameter K3 manifolds in terms of elliptic integrals. The resulting expressions are globally valid throughout the moduli space and allow the explicit inversion of the mirror map and the exact computation of distances, useful for checks of the Swampland Distance Conjecture. We comment on the generalization to multi-parameter models and provide a two-parameter example.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swampland Conjectures for an Almost Topological Gravity Theory</title>
      <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/swampland-conjectures-almost-topological-gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/swampland-conjectures-almost-topological-gravity/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;with Ralph Blumenhagen, Christian Kneißl, Andriana Makridou and Lorenz Schlechter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We analyze AdS and dS swampland conjectures in a three-dimensional higher spin theory with self-interacting matter, which contains conformal gravity and is almost topological. A theory of a similar type was proposed as the effective theory in the high energy phase of non-critical M-theory in 3D. With some details differing from the usual string theory story, it is found that the resulting effective theory, namely topologically massive gravity, fits well into the web of the proposed swampland conjectures. Supporting a recent proposal, in particular we find that this 3D theory gives rise to a quantum break time that scales like \(t_Q\sim H^{-1}\).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Flux Superpotentials for Type IIB Flux Vacua Close to a Conifold</title>
      <link>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/small-flux-superpotentials-conifold/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.algarafa.com/es/publications/small-flux-superpotentials-conifold/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;with Ralph Blumenhagen, Max Brinkmann and Lorenz Schlechter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We generalize the recently proposed mechanism by Demirtas, Kim, McAllister and Moritz &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.10047&#34;&gt;arXiv:1912.10047&lt;/a&gt; for the explicit construction of type IIB flux vacua with \(|W_0|\ll 1\) to the region close to the conifold locus in the complex structure moduli space. For that purpose tools are developed to determine the periods and the resulting prepotential close to such a codimension one locus with all the remaining moduli still in the large complex structure regime. As a proof of principle we present a working example for the Calabi-Yau manifold \(\mathbb{P}_{1,1,2,8,12}[24]\).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>